<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>CS 152, Spring 2023 on Aditya's notes</title><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs152/</link><description>Recent content in CS 152, Spring 2023 on Aditya's notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://saligrama.io/notes/cs152/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs152/2023-04-03-intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs152/2023-04-03-intro/</guid><description>Trust and Safety Engineering # What is Trust and Safety? # The study of how people abuse the results to cause harm Often using products the way they are designed to work Crosses between specialties &amp;ndash; requires understanding of society and humanity Dynamic and unpredictable Course goals # Have empathy for a broad cross section of the people who use your products and the risks they face Explain to software engineers and product managers the common ways that internet technologies are used to cause harm Recognize the pattern of how long-existing societal challenges (hate speech, disinformation, child abuse) can be amplified by internet technologies Understand how to anticipate safety risks for a proposed product Design and implement a functional abuse reporting flow powered by a machine learning classifier T&amp;amp;S Challenges # Scale How to reason about human-created issues at billions-scale?</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs152/2023-04-05-design-for-trust-and-safety/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs152/2023-04-05-design-for-trust-and-safety/</guid><description>Designing for Trust, Safety, and Privacy # Guest lecture: Karen Maxim, Policy &amp;amp; Law Enforcement Response Team Lead at Zoom Trust &amp;amp; Safety
Initially: Zoom as a B2B company &amp;ndash; for companies to meet other companies + clients &amp;ldquo;Closed meeting space&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; not designed for wider things like classrooms and city council meetings Did not need much in the way of T&amp;amp;S function First set of reports: &amp;ldquo;Illicit Content and Substances&amp;rdquo; (ICS), sex/drugs parties, needed to shut down, but predictable work Zoom T&amp;amp;S: established in response to crisis of zoom-bombing @ beginning of pandemic Basic definitions # Surface: a technical &amp;ldquo;entry point&amp;rdquo; to interact with a system e.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs152/2023-04-10-authentication-and-identity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs152/2023-04-10-authentication-and-identity/</guid><description>Authentication and Identity # Digital identity mappings:
Organization &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; infrastructure Phishing MITM attacks Typo squatting Mismatched domains Internationalized domain name (IDN) homograph attack Email security User &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; account Stealing passwords Cracked breached password databases Credential stuffing Malware / Trojans Account &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; real human Black markets allow for specialization of effort:
Markets for stolen data Malware Phish kits Hacking for hire Botnets Authentication and Authorization # Authentication (authn) - Whether users are who they claim to be Authorization (authz) - What users are and aren&amp;rsquo;t allowed to access Authentication: idenification + challenges (e.</description></item></channel></rss>