<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>CS 251, Fall 2022 on Aditya's notes</title><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs251/</link><description>Recent content in CS 251, Fall 2022 on Aditya's notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://saligrama.io/notes/cs251/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs251/2022-09-26-intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs251/2022-09-26-intro/</guid><description>CS 251 Blockchain and Cryptocurrency Technologies # This course # Brings together: cryptography, distributed systems, economics Course organization # The starting point: Bitcoin mechanics Consensus protocols Ethereum and decentralized applications DeFi: decentralized applications in finance Private transactions on a public blockchain: SNARKs and zero-knowledge proofs Scaling the blockchain: getting to 10K transactions/sec Interoperability among chains: bridges and wrapped coins What is a blockchain? # Consensus layer: public append-only data structure Persistence: can never remove added data Safety: all honest participants have same data Liveness: honest participants can add new transactions Open: anyone can add data (no authentication) Not strict requirement How are blocks added to chains?</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs251/2022-09-28-bitcoin-mechanics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/cs251/2022-09-28-bitcoin-mechanics/</guid><description>Bitcoin mechanics # Overview of the Bitcoin consensus layer # Miners broadcast received transaction (Tx) to peer-to-peer (P2P) network Every miner validates received Tx and stores them in its mempool (unconfirmed Tx set) Implication: miners see all Tx before posted on chain Every ~10 minutes: Each miner creates a candidate block from Tx in its mempool A &amp;ldquo;random&amp;rdquo; miner is selected and broadcasts its block to P2P network Selected miner is paid 6.</description></item></channel></rss>