<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>INTLPOL 268, Fall 2021 on Aditya's notes</title><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/</link><description>Recent content in INTLPOL 268, Fall 2021 on Aditya's notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-09-20-intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-09-20-intro/</guid><description>Class structure # Timing # Monday 11:30am-1:00pm: Tech lecture by Alex Wednesday 11:30am-1:30pm: Law lecture by Riana Friday 1:30pm-2:30pm: Lab section by Austin Grading # 25% - weekly legal short response (due 11:59pm Tuesday) 25% - weekly lab assignments (due 11:00am Monday) 50% - exams May be curves upward for reasonable distribution
Exams # Take-home exam: take between Oct 20 and Oct 24 4hr to complete what should be a 2hr exam Technical and legal topics Multiple-choice, short-ansewr, practical challenges from labs Open note and open reading Final exam - in person at time TBA Technical and legal topics - biased towards post-midterm topics Multiple-choice, short-ansewr, practical challenges from labs Open note and open reading Offensive security # &amp;ldquo;Hacking&amp;rdquo;: Manipulating a system of hardware and software to do something unintended by the designer or owner of that system Motivations for hacking: Revolutions like Arab Spring, to overthrow authoritarian governments Authoritarian governments formed after Arab Spring, for societal control Nation-states, to destabilize and compete with other countries Individuals and organizations, either for financial (i.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-09-22-legal-intro-and-electronic-communications-privacy-act/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-09-22-legal-intro-and-electronic-communications-privacy-act/</guid><description>Legal intro # Course assignments: Short responses # Assigned Wednesday lecture; due 11:59pm following Tuesday Max 400 words Discussion with other students allowed but need to submit alone Grading: &amp;ldquo;needs improvement,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;meets expectations,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;exceeds expectation&amp;rdquo; Cyber issue forces at play # Pathetic Dot theory: Market, Law, Norms, Architecture
Industry standards, compliance bodies, self-regulatory schemes
ISO27001 - infosec management standards; can become legal req by law or contract PCI DSS - anti CC fraud Digital Advertising Alliance - ad industry self-reg body Tech companies enforcing standards + policing behavior</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-09-27-web-requests-and-attacks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-09-27-web-requests-and-attacks/</guid><description>Web requests # GET requests # Useful for simple requests: retrieving a resource for a server; example: search
GET&amp;rsquo;s are idempotent: same request is the same every time; should not change server state GET fields are limited to the URI Single Sign On # Allows user to log into multiple websites with only one login system
Advantages:
Single security implementation; only one login account needs to be maintained Single point of failure Allows security team at SSO provider to shut down suspicious login requests on other sites Can force 2FA on multiple sites if SSO provider enforces it POST requests # For changing server state; contains URI but also can have much more fields that are not contained in the URI</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-09-29-ecpa-for-private-actors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-09-29-ecpa-for-private-actors/</guid><description>ECPA Continued # ECPA liability for private actors # Does WiFi &amp;ldquo;sniffing&amp;rdquo; violate the Wiretap Act? Statute: Not unlawful to intercept an electronic communication when readily accessible to general public This is to prevent penalizing radio hobbyists for listening in on radio frequencies Court: No! In re Innovatio IP Ventures, LLC Patent Litig., 886 F. Supp. 2d 888 (N.D. III 2012) Innovatio, a patent troll, used a &amp;ldquo;packet capture adapter&amp;rdquo; intercepted packets sent over WiFi to fish for IP violations on public WiFi networks Capture included content, not just metadata Court ruled this is not unlawful since it falls inside private interception exception Opinion held that sniffing public unencrypted WiFi comms is easy and cheap, so these comms are &amp;ldquo;readily accessible to the general public&amp;rdquo; Court: Maybe!</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-04-cyberattacks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-04-cyberattacks/</guid><description>Anatomy of a Cyberattack # Classifying cyber actors # What can they do? (skill) Who are they? (attribution) Why? (goals) Money Political motivations Anarchy Leads to the question of: How can we deter them?
Types of state cyber actors # Superpowers: Five Eyes (US, UK, AU, CA, NZ); CH (Mandiant APT 1, APT 17); RU (Mandiant APT 28, APT 29); IL; FR, DE, NL (?) Large, well-funded professional organizations Full-spectrum operations including HUMINT Advanced, self-driving malware with 0-days Careful operational security (ability to not get caught) Rapid Risers: IR, KP, VE, SK Rapidly improving via investment and foreign help Often using cyber to level playing field Might have 0-day, often new malware Learn quickly from the superpowers The Peleton (IN, PK, SA, BR, TR) Cyber capabilities seen as part of national power Skilled, but perhaps smaller, teams Often dependent on private groups, superpowres Poised to break out with right investment Ambitious buyers (MX, ET, AE) Purchasing both software and often operations Limited in-house development Likely to use cyber power domestically Nation-state control # Most control: US, UK Offensive operations under direct control with legal guidelines Non-authorized hacking prosecuted More control: IN, SK Pro-government operations carriedout by independent group with tight controls Mixture: CH, TR, IL Mixture of first and third-party operations Independent groups allowed to operate but tightly controlled Less control: RU, VE Mixture of first and third-party operations Independent groups encouraged to go rogue, internal politics can be dangerous Lawless: NG, RO Hackers operate for pure profit motive, government cannot/will not intervene Cyber Kill Chain # Reconnaissance: Planning phase of operation; research on targets Weaponization: Preparation and staging phase of operation; automated generation of malware; weaponizer couples malware and exploit into a deliverable payload Delivery: Adversaries convey malware to the target Exploitation: Adversaries must exploit vulnerability to gain access (0-days) Installation: Adversaries install persistent backdoor in victim environment to maintain extended access Command and Control (C2): Malware opens a command channel to enable adversary to remotely manipulate the victim With hands-on keyboard access, intruders accomplish the mission&amp;rsquo;s goal Social engineering is much simpler: can accomplish goals (information theft) with only first 4 steps; phishing payload is easy to create.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-06-computer-fraud-and-abuse-act/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-06-computer-fraud-and-abuse-act/</guid><description>Computer Fraud and Abuse Act (CFAA) # TW: Suicide
Key concepts # &amp;ldquo;Access without authorization&amp;rdquo; Not defined in the statute &amp;ldquo;Exceeding authorized access&amp;rdquo; Defined in the statute yet courts still are inconsistent about interpretting it Recently interpreted by the Supreme Court in Van Buren v. United States Subsections: # a - Seven or more prohibitions (a)(1) Espionage prohibitions (a)(2) Obtaining information from 3 sources: financial/banking/credit institutions, federal govt, or &amp;ldquo;any protected computer&amp;rdquo; (a)(3) Trespass on federal government system (a)(4) Intent to defraud (a)(5) Causes damage (A) knowingly causes transmission of program that intentionally causes damage without authorization to a protected computer (B) intentionally accesses a protected compute rwithout authorization, and as a result of such conduct, recklessly causes damage (C) intentionally accesses a protected computer without authorization, and as a result of such conduct, causes damage and loss (a)(6) Password trafficking (a)(7) Extortion threats to a computer/data Renewed relevance in the age of ransomware b - Attempt and conspiracy c - Sentences for criminal violations d - Secret service power to investigate e - Definitions &amp;ldquo;damage&amp;rdquo;: any impairment to the integrity or availability of a data, a program, a system, or information &amp;ldquo;loss&amp;rdquo;: any reasonable cost to any victim: includes cost of incident response, damage assessment, data/program/system/information restoration, revenue lost, cost incurred, other consequential damages incurred because of interruption of service &amp;ldquo;protected computer*: (e)(2)(A) Financial or federal government computer (e)(2)(B) &amp;ldquo;used in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce or communication&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; any internet-connected computer (e)(2)(C), added 2020: &amp;ldquo;is part of a voting system&amp;rdquo;, either is used for federal election management/support/administration or &amp;ldquo;has moved in or otherwise affects interstate or foreign commerce&amp;rdquo; f - Law enforcementand intelligence agencies exception g - Civil cause of action, negligence exemption h - Reporting to Congress (now expired) i - Forfeiture provisions j - Forfeiture provisions Criminal cases under CFAA # Morris Worm (1988) # One of the first computer worms spread via Internet At least $100,000 in damage ($225,000 in 2021 dollars) Infected ~3-10% of all Internet-connect computers at the time First felony conviction under CFAA (upheld by Second Circuit, 1991) Convicted under then-current version of 1030(a)(5) which was subsequently amended in 1996 Indictments of state-sponsored hackers and look-alikes # China: Dec.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-11-network-security/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-11-network-security/</guid><description>Network Security # How does the internet work? # Packet Switching Break up internet communications messages into packages, release them onto the network, each node in the network forwards it to the next node until reaching the host which reassembles it into the correct order Two universally used protocols: IP - Internet Protocol BGP - Border Gateway Protocol Internal networks can be different (Comcast uses DOCSYS, AT&amp;amp;T uses LTE and 5G) but the networks themselves talk IP/BGP to each other Web layers # Notes:</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-13-cfaa-dmca-and-security-research/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-13-cfaa-dmca-and-security-research/</guid><description>Computer Fraud and Abuse Act (CFAA), continued # hiQ v. LinkedIn (oral arguments Oct. 18, 2021 - remanded to 9th circuit)
hiQ argument: Van Buren&amp;rsquo;s gates up/down inquiry means scraping publicly avail data is OK (gate up) but scraping private data (like in Power Ventures) is not (gate down) C&amp;amp;D letters and counter-bot measures don&amp;rsquo;t count as &amp;ldquo;down gates&amp;rdquo; since info is public LinkedIn argues: Public data counts as &amp;ldquo;authorization&amp;rdquo;, but LinkedIn put the &amp;ldquo;gate down&amp;rdquo; with C&amp;amp;D letter, targeted IP blocks, so after that hiQ access was without aughorization IP blocks are technological or code-based rstrictions on access, per Van Buren footnote 8 Southwest Airlines v.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-20-data-security-laws/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-20-data-security-laws/</guid><description>Data Security and Data Breach Notification Laws # Nothing comprehensive at the federal level; states have all the power here.
State Data Breach Notification Laws # Each state, plus DC/PR/VI/GU have one Laws share many commonalities, but plenty of variation Discovering/being notified of a &amp;ldquo;breach of the security of the system&amp;rdquo; triggers duty to notify Any state resident whose &amp;ldquo;personal information&amp;rdquo; (PI) was, or is reasonably believed to have been, acquired by an unauthorized person Definitions comonly used by many states: Breach of security of system: unlawful, unauthorized acquisition of PI PI: first name/initial + last name + 1 more of SSN, DL/ID card number, account/credit/debit number + pin/code/password Laws generally apply to computerized data that includes PI Excludes publicly available information lawfully made available to the public by government or media Many states add more types of info to definitions of PI Ex: in California</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-25-corporate-intrusion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-25-corporate-intrusion/</guid><description>Corporate Intrusion # Privilege escalation # An attacker starts with no privilege and no ability to access anything Initial entry point: sending a fake PDF to a lawyer, sending a fake Excel spreadsheet to an accountant, etc Attackers want to end with privileges necessary for their objectives Escalation may happen remotely or locally Computer privilege levels # Limited accounts (jails) - programs run with limited privileges to trap any attackers who successfully compromise them Normal user account - ability to run programs and access data in home and shared directories; but cannot install software and access data from other users Administrator/root - highest privileged user account, can access anything on the device but cannot necessarily modify OS itself Service accounts - used by software that runs in the background, has lots of power but cannot modify running system System/kernel - fully privileged to interact directly with hardware, access all data, modify running system Managed systems # Computers on a corporate network are managed by a central authority (i.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-27-ransomware-and-foreign-hackers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-10-27-ransomware-and-foreign-hackers/</guid><description>Ransomware and Foreign Hackers # TW: discussion of death of a baby
The recent ransomware boom # Why is ransomware so big now? Cryptocurrency.
Ransoms have been around for a long time, so has malware Historically, ransomware was used to hit small businesses and charge hundreds of dollars to recover data However, hackers now routinely extort critical infrastructure providers (gas pipelines, transportation systems, etc) for hundreds of millions of dollars Cryptocurrency is easier to obtain, transact, convert to real currency Exchanges are less uptight than backs about KYC (Know Your Customer)/AML (Anti Money Laundering) laws People generally think cryptocurrency is untraceable However: this myth was busted in June 2021 after FBI recovered 63.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-01-cryptography/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-01-cryptography/</guid><description>Cryptography # Definitions # Cryptography: the study of secret or secure communications Cryptology: the study of math behind cryptography Cryptanalysis: code-breaking Plaintext: an unencrypted input/output of a cryptosystem Cryptotext: the encrypted output of a cryptosystem Goals of cryptosystems:
Confidentiality: keeping information private or secret Integrity: ensuring that information has not been modified Authentication: proving somebody is who they say they are Non-repudiation: proving that a message was sent by a specific actor Modern cryptography definitions # Key primitives # Key exchange: allows you to agree on a secret number Symmetric cipher: encrypts data using a shared key Block cipher: input fixed message size (for DES, 64 bits) Stream cipher: encrypts data one bit at a time Asymmetric cipher: encrypts/decrypts data with different keys Diffie-Hellman (DH): generate shared key from individual public/private keys Rivest-Shamir-Adleman (RSA): encrypt message using public key/private key Hash algorithm: generates a fingerprint for data Function that creates a &amp;ldquo;fingerprint&amp;rdquo; of an arbitrary input that is deterministic, fixed length, and very difficult to reverse Digital signature: proves that data was sent by holder of private key Building blocks of modern cryptography # Digital signatures: proof of identity of users/server Key exchange protocol: share secret key between users/user and server Symmetric cipher: use the secret key to encrypt/decrypt messages Hashes and signatures: make sure the message hasn&amp;rsquo;t been tampered with Uses of encryption # Transport encryption: create a secure tunnel (e.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-03-cyber-conflict/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-03-cyber-conflict/</guid><description>Cyber conflict # Nation-state-level hacking # Motivations # Financial gain (IP theft, economic development) Information collection (espionage) Covert action (information operations, sabotage) Armed conflict (if there is one already, or to start one) &amp;ldquo;Prepare the battlefield&amp;rdquo; - gain access to targeted system now to take action on it later &amp;ldquo;Hold at risk&amp;rdquo; - deterrence measures; let other side know you can damage their asset Retaliation options # Ignore it Make threatening noises, but don&amp;rsquo;t do anything (i.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-08-dark-web-and-cryptocurrencies/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-08-dark-web-and-cryptocurrencies/</guid><description>The Dark Web # Internet routing # The ideal: anarchism; &amp;ldquo;The Net interprets censorship as damage and routes around it&amp;rdquo; In reality: a few centralized providers maintain infrastructure for all internet communications A LOT of traffic flows through the US NSA saw this as an opportunity for surveillance Also: China&amp;rsquo;s censorship is extremely effective! Can do blocking on traffic that leaves Chinese servers A solution has been to use VPNs, though blocking tech has gotten better The Onion Router (TOR) # Web browser that communicates (encrypted) with a series of nodes that forward traffic, eventually to exit node and to unencrypted open internet TOR is in an arms race with the PRC; PRC tries to shut down TOR access .</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-10-encryption-and-technical-assistance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-10-encryption-and-technical-assistance/</guid><description> Encryption # US Encryption Law, 1970s-1990s # Encryption used to be regulated as a &amp;ldquo;munition&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Export-grade&amp;rdquo; cryptography forced by federal regulations to be weaker than cryptography for US market Regulations eventually relaxed around 2000 Still export controls for software with cryptographic functionality (but now loosening) Free-speech challenges by CS professors Bernstein v. U.S. DOJ (9th Cir. 1999) Junger v. Daley (6th Cir. 2000) Impact on modern-day web security FREAK attack (export-grade RSA) Logjam attack (export-grade Diffie-Hellman) DROWN attack (export-grade RSA)</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-15-malware/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-15-malware/</guid><description>Malware # Definitions # Malware: umbrella term for malicious software
Virus: a malicious program that infects other program, usually spreading with human assistance Worm: a malicious program that spreads automatically, often without human intervention Trojan Horse: a malicious program that pretends to be something innocuous Rootkit: software that provides an adversary access to a computer in a hidden manner Specifically: control the computer at a system or kernel level RAT (Remote Access Toolkit): a rootkit that is often optimmized for ease-of-use A history of malware # Once upon a time (Commodore 64 era), viruses were carried on a floppy disk Inserting it would cycle colors and display a message At this time, there was no way to make money with malware, so viruses were mostly cute pranks Wipers: early destructive malware Floppy disk, would erase MSDOS disk The Morris Worm: the first fully automated worm Released by Robert Morris Jr.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-17-government-hacking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-17-government-hacking/</guid><description>Government Hacking # Specifically: governments hacking individuals for law enforcement purposes
Tools in law enforcement&amp;rsquo;s investigative toolbox (Easy to Hard)
Traditional evidence-gathering: warrants, ECPA, etc: Evidence is readily available Compelled technical assistance: Make provider repurpose a product feature for law enforcement purposes Government hacking: Using a bug for law enforcement purposes without provider participation Overview # Usual authority: search and seizure warrant (Fed. R. Crim. Pro. 41) Maybe no warrant needed if LE is only collecting IP address, according to multiple courts (have no reasonable expectation of privacy in IP address) State law may compel: Cal ECPA requires LE to get warrant for IP addresses Since Dec.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-29-new-frontiers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://saligrama.io/notes/intlpol268/2021-11-29-new-frontiers/</guid><description>New Frontiers # China # 5 of the largest Internet platforms are Chinese TikTok: first to become dominant globally without Chinese government help PRC-based companies: Have to deal with political content moderation requirements Less experienced with safety issues as Western companies are Are not experienced with Western privacy laws Might store data in the PRC Could decide to not follow ECPA Crackdown on PRC-based tech CEOs that publicly disagree with CCP policies or that present a threat to Xi Jinping&amp;rsquo;s power Synthetic Media # Example: DNC email hack in 2016 Can create fake Facebook/Twitter profiles to mislead Types of abuse where falsity isn&amp;rsquo;t relevant to impact: Fake accounts Sextortion Harassment Spam Hate speech NCII These are ripe grounds for deepfakes IOT # Everything is a computer!</description></item></channel></rss>